A Guide to the Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection, 1848-1939
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection, 1848-1939
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2010-067
0.3 cu. ft. 1 box; 1 oversize folder
Family papers of President John Tyler, his second wife, Julia Gardiner Tyler, and descendants, mostly through the couple's daughter, Pearl Tyler Ellis. Letters written to the Tylers from family and friends; a letter written by the Tyler's son, David G. Tyler; an autograph book used at the 1868 Democratic National Convention; a published memorial to Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner Horsford; photographs of Pearl Tyler Ellis; Ellis and Marye family-related newspaper clippings; photographs and Civil War prisoner parole of Confederate Major William Gordon Anderson.
Marye, Madison
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2007.
Biographical Note
John Tyler, tenth president of the United States, was born in Charles City County, Virginia in 1790, the son of John and Mary Armistead Tyler. Admitted to the Virginia bar in 1809, Tyler established a practice in his native county. He was elected the the Virginia House of Delegates in 1811. In 1813 he married Letitia Christian (also born in 1790), and the couple would have eight children. Elected to Congress in 1816, Tyler served until 1821, then returned to the Virginia House of Delegates, then was elected Virginia governor in 1824, then served in the U. S. Senate from 1827 until 1836, when he resigned. Elected vice-president as William Henry Harrison's running mate in 1840, Tyler became president soon after taking office, following Harrison's death on April 4, 1841. Letitia Christian Tyler died the following year, and in 1844, Tyler married Julia Gardiner, making her First Lady of the United States. John Tyler died in 1862.
Born on Gardiner's Island, New York in 1820, Julia was the daughter of David and Juliana McLachlan-Gardiner. Together, the John and Julia Gardiner Tyler had seven children: David, John, Julia, Lachlan, Lyon, Robert and Pearl. After Tyler's presidency, the couple moved to Sherwood Forest, their Charles City County estate. Following President Tyler's death, Julia Tyler moved to Staten Island, New York, though her sympathies lay with the Confederacy. In the 1870s, she returned to Virginia, her finances largely depleted, and lived with the aid of her children. She died in Richmond in 1872.
Pearl Tyler, the youngest child of John and Julia Gardiner Tyler, was born on June 20, 1860. She married William Munford Ellis, a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, in 1884. Born in Richmond in 1846, Ellis was the son of Powhatan Lewis Ellis and Elvira Henry Munford. His father died while Ellis was still a boy, and he moved with his mother and stepfather, Howard Peyton, to Montgomery County, Virginia in 1853. In 1864, William Ellis enlisted in the 4th Regiment, Virginia Reserves at Christiansburg, Virginia. He was elected second lieutenant in Company A in early 1864 and later appointed adjutant. Ellis first married, in 1870, Margaret Kent Langhorne, with whom he had four children before she died in 1882. Married in 1884, William and Pearl Tyler Ellis lived for many years in the Shawsville, Virginia area and had eight children: Pearl, John, Leila, Cornelia, Gardiner, William, Julia, and Lyon. Pearl Tyler Ellis served in the U. S. Army Nurse Corps during World War I and World War II, eventually attaning the rank of lieutenant colonel. Pearl Tyler Ellis died in Richmond in 1947; William Mumford Ellis had died in 1921.
Among the children of William and Pearl Tyler Ellis was Leila MacLachlan Ellis (1888-1968). She married Ambrose Madison Marye (1887-1972). The couple lived in the Shawsville, Virginia area. Ambrose Marye was the son of Alfred J. Marye and Nancy A. Anderson, whose brother, William G. Anderson, had served as a major in the 54th Virginia Infantry.
Scope and Content
This collection contains papers of Julia Gardiner Tyler, wife of President John Tyler, and some of her descendants, mostly through daughter Pearl Tyler Ellis. Though small, the collection is comprised of a wide array of items, including correspondence, printed material, photographs and ephemera. Among the papers relating directly to the John and Julia Tyler family is an 1844 letter to President Tyler from an anonymous woman, offering congratulations on his recent marriage. Also included are several letters addressed to Julia Tyler, among which is a war-time letter from a soldier named Douthat, a Confederate prisoner-of-war at Point Lookout, Maryland. Also included are a letter from nephew John C. Tyler regarding timber interests; a letter from son John Alexander Tyler, written from Baden, Germany; a letter from William A. Galbraith, enclosing tickets to the 1868 National Democratic Convention; two letters from Pearl Tyler Ellis (including an 1885 letter written from Shawsville, Virginia); and an undated letter from F. W. Thomas, addressed to "Lady Presidentiss" and regarding invitations to be issued to the Beeckmans and Colegates for an unidentified event. Also among the Tyler correspondence is a letter from David G. Tyler (oldest child of John and Julia Gardiner Tyler) to Harry Beeckman and accompanied by an envelope addressed to Mrs. David Gardiner and free-franked by John Tyler. Included also is an autograph book used by Julia Tyler at the 1868 Democratic National Convention (containing the autographs of delegates from Virginia, North Carolina, and Arkansas, and accompanied by a delegate ribbon); an invitation to the 1848 National [Washington's] Birth-night Ball; and a published memorial to Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner Horsford (including studio portrait). The Tyler-related papers also contain several empty envelopes, among which are three envelopes free-franked by Tyler and two black-edged mourning envelopes addressed to Tyler as president.
Among the items in the collection related to the Ellis family are photographs of Pearl Tyler Ellis (including one with husband William Munford Ellis), several family-related newspaper clippings, and a lock of hair from Carlton Munford (brother of Elvira Munford Ellis Peyton, William Munford Ellis's mother). A property map of the Shawsville, Virginia area is included in an oversize folder.
From the Marye family, the collection contains several family-related newspapers clippings, a letter from W. Carter Wormeley to Bob Marye, a report on the Works Progress Administration's Engineering and Construction Division by Ambrose M. Marye, two photographs of scenes on the Virginia Tech campus, and a copy of an 1862 letter from Nannie E. Kent to Mrs. James McGavock Kent. Also included here are two 20th-century studio portraits of Major William Gordon Anderson, who served with the 54th Virginia Infantry during the Civil War and was the brother of Nancy Anderson Marye. Accompanying the portraits is Anderson's 1865 military parole.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to family unit, then by document type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books were removed from the Tyler-Ellis-Marye Family Collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Adams, Daniel, Arithmetic: in which the principles of operating by numbers are analytically explained, and synthetically applied... (Keene, NH: J. and J. W. Prentiss, 1833). QA101 A24 1833 Small Spec
Affection's gift: a Christmas and New Year's present for youth (Philadelphia: Thomas T. Ash, 1835). AY11 P4 1835 Small Spec
Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, Songs and scenes from Goethe's Faust (Boston: Estes and Lauriat, 1884). PT2026 F2 M47 1884 Large Spec
Index Terms
Local Subjects:
Civil War; Local/Regional History; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- Letter to [John Tyler] from anonymous (Norfolk, Virginia), 1844. (Box-folder 1-1)
- Letters to Julia Gardiner Tyler, 1864-1885, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - From Douthat (Point Lookout, [Maryland]), 1864.
  - from Jn [John] C. Tyler (Sherwood Forest), 1866.
  - from A. Winant (Rossville, New York), 1864.
  - from William Watson (New York, New York) to Gurdon Bradley, 1867.
  - from J. Alex Tyler (Baden, Germany), 1867.
  - from [William] A. Galbraith (New York, New York), 1868.
  - from Pearl Tyler (Richmond, Virginia), 1884.
  - from Pearl T. Ellis ("Madison," [Shawsville, Virginia p.m.]), 1885.
  - from F. W. Thomas, n.d.
- Letter from David G. Tyler (Sherwood Forest) to Harry Beeckman, 1859. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Julia Tyler autograph book, 1868. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Envelopes. (Box-folder 1-5)
  - To Mrs. Juliana Gardiner, Staten Island, New York (postmarked Richmond, Virginia), 1859., [free-franked by John Tyler]
  - To John Tyler, president (postmarked New York, Nov. 2), n.d., [on mourning stationery]
  - To "His Excellency, the President of the United States" (postmarked New York, Aug. 3), n.d., [on mourning stationery]
  - To Ex-president Tyler (postmarked May 7, New York), n.d.
  - To Margaret G. Beeckman, Staten Island, New York (postmarked Norfolk, Virginia, June 13), [free-franked by John Tyler]
  - To Mrs. Juliana Gardiner, Saratoga Springs, New York (postmarked Norfolk, Virginia, Jul 5), n.d., [free-franked by John Tyler]
- Printed material. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Invitation to National Birth-night Ball, 1848.
  - Mary L'Hommedieu Gardiner Horsford memorial, 1872. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Ellis family papers, 1919-1922, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - William Munford Ellis and Pearl Tyler Ellis studio portrait, n.d.
  - Pearl Ellis snapshot, n.d.
  - [Pearl Tyler Ellis] studio portraits n.d., [2 items]
  - Lock of hair from Carlton Munford, brother of Elvira H. Peyton, n.d.
  - Newspaper clippings.
    - death of Lt. Carlton R. Munford (unidentified newspapers), [1847?]., [photocopies][2 items]
    - Death announcement and obituary for Benjamin Howard Peyton (unidentified newspapers), [1868]., [photocopies] [2 items]
    - "'Victory Girl,' Carnival Prize Win[ner]" ( The Evening Star), 1919., [photocopy]
    - "Major William Munford Ellis (a Tribute)" (unidentified newspaper), [1921?]., [photocopy]
    - "Major W. M. Ellis is buried at Shawsville" (unidentified newspaper), [1921?]., [photocopy]
    - Photograph of William M. Ellis and children Munford, John, Gardiner and Pearl in military uniforms ( American Legion Weekly, 1922.
    - "Mrs. Pearl Ellis is Critically Ill" (unidentified newspaper), n.d., [photocopy]
    - "Senatorial Nomination" (unidentified newspaper), n.d., [photocopy]
    - "Veterans to Play: Champoin 'Fiddler' and Banjo Player to Entertain press Club" (unidentified newspaper), n.d., [photocopy]
- Marye family papers, 1865-1939, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Letter to Bob [Marye] from [W. Carter Wormeley], 1930.
  - Newspaper clippings.
    - "First at Gettysburg and Last at Appomattox" (unidentified newspaper) n.d., [photocopy]
    - "Alfred James Marye" (unidentified newspaper) 1920., [photocopy]
    - "Poetic Veteran's Check Was Sent" (unidentified newspaper) n.d., [photocopy]
  - "Engineering and Construction Division, the Work Projects Administration: Its Handicaps, Mistakes, and Accomplishments" by A. M. Marye, n.d.
  - Photographs of Virginia Tech airport and agricultural building, 1939., [2 items]
  - William G. Anderson Civil War prisoner parole, 1865.
  - William G. Anderson studio portraits, n.d., [2 items]
  - Transcription of 1862 letter from Nannie E. Kent to Mrs. James McGavock Kent, n.d.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS. (Folder 1)
  - Shawsville, Virginia area map, n.d.